A Finding Aid to the Holger Cahill Papers, 1910-1993, bulk 1910-1960, in the Archives of American Art AAA.cahiholg
Archives of American Art
- Writings, Lectures and Speeches, 1916-1960; Series 4; (Boxes 14-15, 18; 1.0 linear ft.)
  - Typescripts For Art For The Millions, 1936-1940; 4.5
    - Eichenberg, Fritz, Eulogy on the Woodblock, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0136-0139)
    - Gellert, Hugo, Artists Coordination Committee, 1936 (Reel 5292, Frame 0141-0146)
    - Glassgold, C. Adolph, Recording American Design, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0147-0153)
    - Gorky, Arshile, My Murals for the Newark Airport: An Interpretation, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0154-0158)
    - Guglielmi, Louis, After the Locusts, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0159-0162)
    - Hayes, Vertis, The Negro Artist Today, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0163-0167)
    - Hayes, Vertis, The Position of Art in Present Day Society As I See It, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0168-0173)
    - Hiler, Hilaire, An Approach to Mural Decoration, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0174-0177)
    - Hunter, R. Vernon, An Interpretation of Patrocino Barela, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0178-0181)
    - Kopman, Benjamin, Notes on Art, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0182-0185)
    - La More, Chet, The Artists Union of America, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0186-0188)
    - Lemmon, Warren W., Native Arts of the Southwest, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0189-0208)
    - Levine, Jack, Street Scene, circa 1937; (1 of 2) (Reel 5292, Frame 0209-0210)
    - Levine, Jack, Street Scene, circa 1937; (2 of 2) (Reel 5292, Frame 212)
    - Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, Sculpture in Southern California, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0213-0219)
    - McMahon, Audrey, The Federal Art Project and the Artist, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0220-0223)
    - Moylan, Lloyd, Mural Opportunities, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0224-0226)
    - Murray, Hester Miller, Concerning Subject Matter, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0227-0229)
    - Newell, James Michael, The Use of Symbols in Mural Painting, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0230-0237)
    - Norman, Geoffrey, The Development of American Mural Painting, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0238-0244)
    - Olds, Elizabeth, Prints for Mass Production, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0245-0252)
    - Palo-Kangas, John, Thought-Forms in Red Sandstone, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0253-0255)
    - Park, Paul, Photography As An Art, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0256-0259)
    - Parr, Russell C., Reaching for Art, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0260-0265)
    - Quirt, Walter, On Mural Painting, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0266-0269)
    - Rackley, Mildred, The United American Artists, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0270-0281)
    - Richardson, Antonio, [ Social Function of Art - It's Relation to the Public], circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0282-0290)
    - Rothschild, Lincoln, The Artist and Democracy, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0291-0296)
    - Seltzner, Leo, On the Making of the Film "The Technique of Fresco Painting,", circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0297-0299)
    - Smith, David, Modern Sculpture and Society, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0300-0308)
    - Smith, E. Herndon, The Organization of Supervisors of the Federal Art Project, circa 1937-1940 (Reel 5292, Frame 0310-0313)
    - Speck, Walter E., Pottery Methods, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0314-0318)
    - Stavenitz, Alexander R., The Therapy of Art, 1939 (Reel 5292, Frame 0320-0336)
    - Sutton, Harry H., High Noon in Art, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0337-0363)
    - Thorp, George, The Art of Supervising Artists, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0364-0368)
    - Trentham, Eugene, Golden Colorado, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0369-0372)
    - Ward, Lynd, Printmakers to the American People, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0373-0377)
    - Weisenborn, Rudolph, Designing a Diorama for the T.V.A., 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0378-0382)
    - White, Francis Robert, Cultural Frontiers, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0383-0389)
    - Wolff, Robert Jay, Chicago and the Artists' Union, 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 0390-0402)
    - Unidentified Author, The Artists as a Social Worker, circa 1937 (Reel 5292, Frame 211)
- Minutes of Meetings and Panel Discussions, Non-FAP, 1939-1947; Series 5; (Box 15; 5 folders)
  This series documents the proceedings of meetings of the American Handicraft Council, the Arts and Letters Secretariat, the Artists' International Association, and a Conference on the Support of the Visual Arts. There is also a typescript of an American Federation of Arts annual convention panel with notes on Cahill's presentation as part of that panel. Material is arranged in chronological order.
  - American Handicraft Council By-Laws and Meeting Minutes (April 19, 1939, December 20, 1939) (Reel 5288, Frame 0027-0047)
  - Typescript of the American Federation of Arts panel, "How Can We Support an American Art?,", March 18, 1941 (Reel 5292, Frame 0460-0516)
  - Arts and Letters Secretariat Meeting, December 5, 1943 (Reel 5288, Frame 0065-0071)
  - Artists' International Association meeting, "International Co-operation Between Artists," Czechoslovakian Institute, April 22, 1944 (Reel 5288, Frame 0072-0080)
  - Conference on the Support of the Visual Arts, American Academy of Arts and Sciences, Boston, Massachusetts, February 14-15, 1947 (Reel 5288, Frame 0081-0089)
- Notes and Research Material, 1935-1970; Series 6; (Boxes 15-16; 0.25 linear ft.)
  This series contains research material on folk art and folk artists in addition to material that appears to be related to Cahill's criticism of William Francis McDonald's book Federal Relief Administration and the Arts (Ohio State University Press, 1969) sponsored by the American Council of Learned Societies.
  Notes found here are primarily for The Artists' America, an unpublished book by Cahill, and include typescripts of essay fragments and artist biographies, and lists of artists and works of art showing locations and owners. There are also notes relating to the review of the book The Birth of the American Tradition in Art, by Oskar Hagen, handwritten notes relating to Erwin Panofsky and miscellaneous notes.
  - American Council of Learned Societies, circa 1949 (Reel 5292, Frame 0519-0531)
  - Erwin Panofsky, undated (Reel 5292, Frame 0533-0581)
  - Folk Art and Folk Art Dealers, 1935, undated (Reel 5292, Frame 0583-0670)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Reel 1105, Frame 0347-0364)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1935-1970 (Reel 5292, Frame 1317-1435)
  - Notes for The Artists' America, circa 1941-1946 (Reel 5292, Frame 0959-1315)
  - Notes for Book Review, The Birth of the American Tradition, by Unidentified Author for The New Republic, circa 1940 (Reel 5292, Frame 0953-0958)
- Artwork, undated; Series 7; (Boxes 16, 18; 2 folders)
  Artwork in this series consists of four undated drawings of animals by Walt Speck, an undated pen and ink drawing by an unidentified artist of an artist sketching in front of a house, and an undated drawing and a lithograph by unidentified artists.
  - Artwork, undated (Reel 5292, Frame 1436-1445)
- Printed Material, 1910-1985; Series 8; (Boxes 16-17; 1.8 linear ft.)
  This series consists of news clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, press releases, prospectuses, calendars of events, programs, brochures, booklets, books, government publications and reproductions of artwork. Much of the material dated between 1935 and 1943 relates to the WPA FAP. News clippings contain copies of approximately thirty articles, including book reviews, written by Cahill for a variety of publications between 1921 and 1960. Some of the material contains hand-written notes.
  - Brochures, undated (Reel 5296, Frame 0325-0345)
  - Booklets, 1925-1941 (Reel 5296, Frame 0347-0431)
  - Books, Federal Sponsored Community Art Centers, undated (Reel 5296, Frame 0434-0490)
  - Books, American Painting, by Holger Cahill, undated (Reel 5296, Frame 0492-0506)
  - Books, George O. "Pop" Hart, Edited with Introduction by Holger Cahill, 1928 (Reel 5296, Frame 0508-0550)
  - Books, Primitives: Poems and Woodcuts, by Max Weber, 1926 (Reel 5296, Frame 0552-0572)
  - Books, The Arts of Painting and Sculpture, by Roger Fry, 1932 (Reel 5296, Frame 0574-0579)
  - Books, Work For Artists: What? Where? How?, Edited by Elizabeth McCausland, 1947 (Reel 5296, Frame 0581-0688)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1935-1943 (Reel 5295, Frame 0567-0665)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1922-1929 (Reel 5295, Frame 0666-0725)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1930-1933 (Reel 5295, Frame 0726-0757)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1934 (Reel 5295, Frame 0758-0808)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1935 (Reel 5295, Frame 0809-0828)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1936 (Reel 5295, Frame 0829-0956)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1937 (Reel 5295, Frame 0957-1043)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, January-April 1938 (Reel 5295, Frame 1044-1099)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, May-July 1938 (Reel 5295, Frame 1100-1125)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, August-December 1938 (Reel 5295, Frame 1126-1149)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, January-March 1939 (Reel 5295, Frame 1150-1197)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, April-August 1939 (Reel 5295, Frame 1198-1240)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, September 1939 (Reel 5295, Frame 1241-1300)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, October-December 1939 (Reel 5296, Frame 0004-0034)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940 (Reel 5296, Frame 0035-0087)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1941-1947 (Reel 5296, Frame 0088-0140)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1952-1967 (Reel 5296, Frame 0141-0160)
  - Government Publications, 1933-1937 (Reel 5296, Frame 0690-0725)
  - Government Publications, 1938 (Reel 5296, Frame 0727-0745)
  - Government Publications, 1939 (Reel 5296, Frame 0813-0815)
  - Government Publications, 1942-1943 (Reel 5296, Frame 0864-0909)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Reel 5296, Frame 0959-0966)
  - News Clippings, undated (Reel 5294, Frame 0800-0904)
  - News Clippings, 1910, 1918-1919 (Reel 5294, Frame 0905a-0905r)
  - News Clippings, 1920-1922 (Reel 5294, Frame 0905s-0945)
  - News Clippings, 1923-1929 (Reel 5294, Frame 0947-0987)
  - News Clippings, 1930-1931 (Reel 5294, Frame 0988-1012)
  - News Clippings, 1932 (Reel 5294, Frame 1013-1051)
  - News Clippings, 1933 (Reel 5294, Frame 1052-1083)
  - News Clippings, 1934 (Reel 5294, Frame 1084-1122)
  - News Clippings, 1935 (Reel 5294, Frame 1123-1145)
  - News Clippings, January-October 1936 (Reel 5294, Frame 1147-1189)
  - News Clippings, October 1-3, 1936 (Reel 5294, Frame 1190-1205)
  - News Clippings, October 4-8, 1936 (Reel 5294, Frame 1206-1225)
  - News Clippings, October 9-13, 1936 (Reel 5294, Frame 1226-1245)
  - News Clippings, October 14-17, 1936 (Reel 5294, Frame 1246-1261)
  - News Clippings, October 18-31, 1936 (Reel 5294, Frame 1262-1277)
  - News Clippings, November-December 1936 (Reel 5294, Frame 1278-1279)
  - News Clippings, January-April 1937 (Reel 5294, Frame 1280-1298)
  - News Clippings, May-August 1937 (Reel 5294, Frame 1299-1315)
  - News Clippings, September-December 1937 (Reel 5294, Frame 1316-1353)
  - News Clippings, January-August 1938 (Reel 5294, Frame 1354-1394)
  - News Clippings, September-October 1938 (Reel 5294, Frame 1396-1421)
  - News Clippings, October-December 1938 (Reel 5295, Frame 0003-0023)
  - News Clippings, January-May 1939 (Reel 5295, Frame 0024-0061)
  - News Clippings, June-August 1939 (Reel 5295, Frame 0062-0079)
  - News Clippings, September-December 1939 (Reel 5295, Frame 0080-0098)
  - News Clippings, 1940 (Reel 5295, Frame 0099-0135)
  - News Clippings, January-June 1941 (Reel 5295, Frame 0136-0164)
  - News Clippings, July-December 1941 (Reel 5295, Frame 0165-0188)
  - News Clippings, 1942 (Reel 5295, Frame 0189-0259)
  - News Clippings, 1943 (Reel 5295, Frame 0260-0276)
  - News Clippings, 1944 (Reel 5295, Frame 0277-0308)
  - News Clippings, 1945 (Reel 5295, Frame 0309-0324)
  - News Clippings, 1946 (Reel 5295, Frame 0326-0372)
  - News Clippings, 1947-1949 (Reel 5295, Frame 0373-0403)
  - News Clippings, 1950-1953 (Reel 5295, Frame 0404-0441)
  - News Clippings, 1954-1955 (Reel 5295, Frame 0442-0470)
  - News Clippings, 1956 (Reel 5295, Frame 0471-0506)
  - News Clippings, 1957-1959 (Reel 5295, Frame 0507-0512)
  - News Clippings, 1960-1969 (Reel 5295, Frame 0513-0549)
  - News Clippings, 1970-1985 (Reel 5295, Frame 0550-0564)
  - Picture Postcards (blank), undated (Reel 5296, Frame 0931-0958)
  - Press Releases (1 of 2), undated (Reel 5296, Frame 0163-0169)
  - Press releases (2 of 2), undated (Reel 5296, Frame 0175-0181)
  - Press releases, 1923 (Reel 5296, Frame 0170-0171)
  - Press releases, 1934 (Reel 5296, Frame 0172-0174)
  - Press releases, 1955 (Reel 5296, Frame 0182-0210)
  - Press releases, 1963 (Reel 5296, Frame 0211-0214)
  - Programs and Calendars of Events, 1935-1945 (Reel 5296, Frame 0242-0323)
  - Programs and Calendars of Events, 1940 (Reel 5292, Frame 0442-0459)
  - Prospectuses, 1934-circa 1941 (Reel 5296, Frame 0217-0239)
  - Reproductions of Artwork, 1939, undated (Reel 5296, Frame 0911-0928)
- Photographs, circa 1917-1960; Series 9; (Box 17; 6 folders)
  This series contains photographs of Cahill and family and colleagues including his mother and sister, Harry Hopkins, Edward Rowan, Eleanor Roosevelt and attendees of an FAP meeting including Stanton MacDonald-Wright. Also found here are photographs of miscellanous artwork. For WPA FAP photographs see 3.14: Photographs.
  - Photographs of Cahill with Family and Colleagues, circa 1917-circa 1950s (Reel 5296, Frame 0968-1018)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Artwork, circa 1930-1960 (Reel 5299, Frame 1126-1155)